A Guide to the Henry Clay Deshields Collection, 1861-1865, 2016
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Henry Clay Deshields Collection, 1861-1865, 2016
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Deshields, Henry Clay, 1832-1884
Deshields, Sarah Furlong Wheelwright, 1833-1901
Ms2017-035
0.7 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
The Henry Clay Deshields Collection contains letters sent to Sarah Deshields from Henry Clay Deshields during his service in the Confederate Army between 1861 and 1865. The collection also contains biographical information on Henry Clay Deshields and the book, Civil War Echoes: Voices from Virginia (1860-1891) by James I. Robertson, Jr. There is also a framed CSA Service Appointment Document dated May 1861.
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Henry Clay Deshields Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2017.
Biographical Note
Henry Clay Deshields was born on April 11, 1832 in Northumberland County, VA. Henry married Sarah Furlong Wheelwright (September 3, 1833-July 6, 1901) on October 18, 1853 in Northumberland County, VA. Together they had 8 children. Henry attended law school at the University of Virginia, then worked as a lawyer and insurance agent. He practiced in Baltimore, MD until the Civil War began. He returned to Virginia and enlisted with the 40th Regiment, Virginia Infantry, Company G, at the rank of Second Lieutenant in May of 1861. He served as a quartermaster and eventually rose to the rank of Captain. On April 9, 1865, Deshields was among those who surrendered on the staff of Field at Appomattox, VA. Henry died on October 16, 1884.
Scope and Content
The Henry Clay Deshields Collection contains letters sent to Sarah Deshields from Henry Clay Deshields during his service in the Confederate Army between 1861 and 1865. The collection also contains biographical information on Henry Clay Deshields and the book, Civil War Echoes: Voices from Virginia (1860-1891) by James I. Robertson, Jr. There is also a framed CSA Service Appointment Document dated May 1861. The letters relate to war happenings including the death of Stonewall Jackson.
There is some variation in the spelling of Deshields' last name, which is reflected in the associated agent (name) record.
Arrangement Note
This collection is organized by material type. The majority of the collection consists of correspondence, which in chronological order.
Rights Statements for Archival Description
The guide to the Henry Clay Deshields Collection by Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, is licensed under a CC0 (https://creativecommons.org/share-your-work/public-domain/cc0/).
Index Terms
Subjects:
Civil War; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Genre and Form Terms:
Correspondence
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1861-02-26-1865-08-27
  - Correspondence, 1861-02-26-1861-12-19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1862-01-06-1862-06-30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1862-07-03-1862-09-24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1862-10-09-1862-12-31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1863-01-04-1863-02-26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1863-03-01-1863-05-22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1863-06-11-1863-07-31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1863-08-05-1863-08-30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1863-09-06-1863-09-27 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1863-10-02-1863-10-29 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1863-11-07-1863-12-30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1864-01-20-1864-03-25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1864-04-01-1864-05-30 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1864-06-01-1864-07-16 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1864-08-02-1864-10-16 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1864-11-03-1864-12-23 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1865-01-15-1865-08-27 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence (2 folders), undated (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
- Biographical Information (Box 1, Folder 20)
- "Civil War Echoes: Voices from Virginia 1860-1891", 2016 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- CSA Military Service Appointment Document, 1861-05 (Box 2)